<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the Citie of London by a lover of truth. Touching the power of a king, and proving out of the word of God, that the authoritie of a king is onely from God and not of man.</title>
            <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E104_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E104[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the Citie of London by a lover of truth. Touching the power of a king, and proving out of the word of God, that the authoritie of a king is onely from God and not of man.</title>
                  <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London Printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 29".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes VIII, 4 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN THE CITIE OF LONDON By a Lover of Truth. Touching the Power of a KING, and proving out of the Word of GOD, that the Authoritie of a King is onely from GOD and not of Man.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ECCL. 8.4.</bibl>
               <p>Where the word of a King is there is power, and who may ſay unto him, what doest thou.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London Printed 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:155937:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155937:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Eccleſ. 8.4.</bibl>
                  <p>Where the word of a <hi>King</hi> is there is power, And who may ſay unto him what doeſt thou.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I ſhall adventure to apply this Text (for to expound it is needleſſe) to ſuch perſons both in Towne and Countrie who make it their only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to but prate rebellious queſtions concerning the priviledges and actions of Kings; I were beſt bee aſſured I can prove my Text to be the expreſſe Word of God, or elſe thoſe people who queſtion Kings will be ſure to queſtion me.</p>
            <p>There is but one that ever queſtioned this Preacher, and if <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> rule be true <hi>Quicunque eſt unus eſt haereticus,</hi> wee muſt rather aſſent to the generall tradition of antiquitie: by the words you will know that one to bee <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> he ſaith this booke is like a man on horſe-backe without boots or ſpurres, never kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a certaine pace: but you all know the driving of that man was like <hi>Iehu,</hi> he drave furiouſly both againſt Church and Kings. Every ſpirit that moved not <hi>Luther</hi> pace, bee it the ſpirit of Solomon the wiſeſt prince in the world, yea although that ſpirit be a freſh inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Gods ſpirit, yet <hi>Ceſſator eſt &amp; ego: calcaribus</hi> but of the two rather thinke <hi>Luthors</hi> tounge wanted a bridle wee therefore in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155937:3"/> feare of God and authority of his holy Church will acknowledge the ſpirit and power of God to be in this booke, and in this Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and will ſay unto our King in the words of the Pſalme <hi>Ride on we wiſh thee good lucke in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Where the word of a <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>IT is well wee finde in Scipture <hi>terminis terminentibus,</hi> or elſe wee might have loſt him. <hi>Ego dixi dij eſtis,</hi> there might be ſome evaſions hence, there is mention of Judges and under-Magiſtrates in the Land <hi>Pſalme</hi> 82.6. they might aſſume this unqueſtioned power and queſtion thoſe whom we call Kings. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> he names ſome in authority, but the Pope may come in for his supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie. In the latter time there are Calvins, <hi>Magiſtratus, Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares, Beza's, ſuperiores poteſtates, Brutus, Iunius optimates regni, Daneus ordines regni, Buchanus publica adminiſtrationis participes. Althaſius, Ephori, Paraus inferiores potestates,</hi> ſo many names as head of the beaſt in the <hi>Apocalip.</hi> But here wee have <hi>Melecke</hi> a King, be not ſubject to ſubjects or inferiour Magiſtrates, but <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecti estote regi tanquam ſupereminenti,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>Whence and what Kings are, are doctrines I thinke ſutable both to this Text and theſe times, their originall is from God a good beginning. <hi>Per me reges regnant</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome.</hi> The ancient forme of ſalutation uſed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was <hi>In eo per quem reges regnant,</hi> then was it not his owne holineſſe <hi>Rex regum</hi> is written upon Chriſt owne thigh <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.16. and <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> his owne firſt type and King was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without father or Mother. Kings are not the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of man but the generation of God, <hi>Ego dixi Dij eſtis.</hi> God help Kings if people undertake to make them, if they may turne Gods <hi>verſe,</hi> to <hi>nos diximus Dij eſtis;</hi> if they may change Chriſts words, <hi>from thou ſhouldest have no power over mee unleſſe it were given thee from above,</hi> to, <hi>thou ſhouldst have no power over me unleſſe it were granted thee</hi> de ſubter, <hi>from beneath.</hi> No all Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are Gods. <hi>Cujus juſſu naſcunter homines, ejus juſſu Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituuntur Principes, Iraen: Inde ſuis poteſtas unde ſpiritus. Tert.</hi> Even all their ornaments and imperiall enſignes are from God.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155937:3"/> 
                  <hi>Diadomae regis in manu dei, Eſay</hi> 62. <hi>His their Crowne, Tupoſuiſti, Pſalme</hi> 21. <hi>Hee puts it on.</hi> The Emperours ſtampe on their Coines was a hand comming forth out of the Clouds holding a Crowne, putting it on their heads. His is their Scepter, <hi>Virga dei in manibus ejus,</hi> His their Throne, <hi>Reges in ſolie coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cat in perpetuum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob. He faſtens them in it for ever;</hi> His alſo their annointing, <hi>Touch not mine Annointed, I have annointed David my ſervant, annointed with oyle for ſupremacie and continuance in his Throne,</hi> not <hi>uncti.</hi> as Prieſts, but <hi>Chriſti Domini,</hi> ſaith the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie three times, ſo ſtiled in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and once in the <hi>New.</hi> Their manner of annointing alſo was diverſe from the Prieſts. They were annointed on the forehead, Kings on the head ſaith <hi>Erotius</hi> in his annotations to <hi>Caſſenders</hi> conſultations, in a word ſaith Saint <hi>August.</hi> they are <hi>uncti ante unctionem,</hi> before we can touch them. v. e. <hi>decreto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Kings whether good or bad they are from God, <hi>Per me Reges regnant</hi> was ſpoken when there was but one good King upon the face of the earth <hi>Solomon. Haec dicit Dominus Cyro uncto meo.</hi> He a Perſian a Heathen. <hi>It repented God of what? that he had made Saul King. Ego dedi vobis in ira mea regem, Hoſ.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Angry I was when I gave you, I gave him through, and there in that honour he must remains though he become</hi> Onus Populi, <hi>an heavie burthen upon the necke of all his ſubjects. Nebuchadnezar who ſlew and kept alive whom he pleaſed,</hi> I gave him, His Majeſty, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>I have raiſed up Pharaoh and placed him in his Throne, to make my power knowne on him who had deſerved it,</hi> that is one ſence whatſoever is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture ſtiles not only <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> Kings, but takes in the reſt: <hi>Hiram,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and <hi>Hadad,</hi> and where the Scripture doth not diſtinguiſh neither may wee, be their religion or manners what pleaſe them, by God they are made, and may not bee marrd by the people—In nature every thing is diſſolved by the ſame meanes it came together, in Law inſtitution, and deſtitution belong to one: in Divinity alſo the Prophet in one and the ſame verſe ſaith, <hi>Ego dedi vobis regem,</hi> in the former, and in one breath, <hi>abstuli eum,</hi> in the latter, <hi>Dominus dedit &amp; Dominus abstulit,</hi> and then, and not till then, the people to ſay <hi>benedictum ſit nomen dei.</hi> And well it is that God hath placed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155937:4"/> them ſo neere himſelfe, <hi>poſt Deum primus ſecundum Deum proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, Tert. Humani Ioves Plant:</hi> the ſubiect then may not come ſo neere him as <hi>Nathan,</hi> to tell him <hi>tu es homo</hi> without <hi>Nathans</hi> Commiſſion, but <hi>tu es Rex, tu es Deus Terra,</hi> a God on earth, ſo neare and ſo one are Kings with God, that the accuſation of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> whereby the ſtory he ſpake nothing of God, but of the King, they bring in the verdict. <hi>Naboth, Maledixi: Deo &amp; Regi,</hi> as if hee could not bu blaſpheme God that ſpake ill of his King, though of <hi>Ahab Nequiſſimus regum.</hi> They are much miſtaken who think that God was offended with the Jewes for choſing royall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in oppoſition to the jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciall or the <hi>Shawhedrim</hi> eſtabliſhed by God under <hi>Moſes,</hi> for Royall government hath beene moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and univerſall in the world, in the Law of nature, before the Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les. Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith therefore, <hi>Eve</hi> was taken out of man, not out of the earth, that mankinde might acknowledge one head, one Superiour, one King, and Sir <hi>Wal. Raleigh</hi> in his ſecond book of the Hiſt. of the world, Royall Government from <hi>Paternall,</hi> which indeed are or ought to bee both in one effect, and ſo we reade of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Patrarch is termed a Prince, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 23.6. And <hi>David</hi> the KING is named a Patriarch, let mee ſpeake boldly to you of <hi>David</hi> the Patriarch: <hi>jus regum</hi> comes from, <hi>jus paternum,</hi> both have one commandement, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy Father,</hi> as God alone rules the whole world, and as the Sunne gives light to all creatures, ſo the people of one Land doe moſt naturally yeeld obedience to one head, one King. All Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were firſt governed by this forme, <hi>Aſſyrians, Greſians, Aegypt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ians, Iewes, Percians, Scythians, Turkes, Tartares, Engliſh, French, Spaniards, Poles, Danes,</hi> and in the <hi>Iudges;</hi> Neither doth ſacred Scripture make mention of other Rulers then Kings. He that will know more in ſo cleere a caſe, may if he pleaſe read <hi>Plato, Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus, Zen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phon,</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Saint <hi>Ierome.</hi> Soveraignty in one perſon, is moſt naturall, moſt reaſonable, moſt honourable, moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, moſt divine; So that God was not angry at the choyce of the kinde of government, but that he thereby was caſt forth from being <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> whom hee in the place of a <hi>King</hi> had governed for above three hundred and fiftie yeares, for neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor the <hi>Sawhedrim</hi> nor any Judge in <hi>Iſrael</hi> had in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155937:4"/> 
                  <hi>jus imperatorium</hi> the Right of a <hi>King,</hi> but onely <hi>jus hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorium &amp; punitivum,</hi> if they tranſgreſſed the written Law of God. God only was their King, who faine would ſtill (beſides the generall protection of the world) have ruled as an earthly King among the reſt, and a patterne to them: but they would no longer live by faith and expectation of his wonted direction in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and deliverance, but rather to be as the Nations round about them, they choſe a man and refuſed the living GOD, Hee is ejected from his immediate Royalty. This the ground of Gods diſpleaſure at the <hi>Iewes</hi> for chooſing them a KING. Ancient and univerſall hath beene the government of the world by Kings. Saint <hi>Ierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in one of his Epiſtles, ſaith that two Governours in a Common-wealth are like <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> two Princes in the wombe of <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſo they in one Kingdome, rend and teare in peeces: <hi>Rome</hi> would not endure two brothers, <hi>In navi unus guberrator in Eccleſia unus Epiſcopus, in Domo unus Dominus, in exercitu unum ſignum, in imperio unus imperator.</hi> The onely way to recover and preſerve unity and peace among us, is one <hi>King.</hi> This for the Originall and antiquitie of Kings whence they are and when.</p>
               <p>Now ſecondly, what they are, which is beſt knowne by that whereby they are <hi>formaliter,</hi> or <hi>finaliter tales,</hi> their power: <hi>Where the Word of a King is, there is power,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Salomon</hi> the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of men as well as Kings, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 8.15. placeth Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creation of the world, better not to bee at all then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no Governement, which is none without power, and that power if to any purpoſe muſt bee ſuch, as with which no earthly power may conteſt, the owner of it, is evermore <hi>Alkum</hi> one againſt whom there ought to bee no riſing, nor any rebellion at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Darius</hi> his three ſervants in <hi>Eſdras</hi> wrote their wiſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Forte est vinum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Fortis est Rex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Fortiores ſurt mulieres; ſed ſupra omnia eſt veritas.</hi> I am ſomewhat afeard it was a Propheſie, they are indeed at this day, ſtronger then our <hi>Darius.</hi> Their fond Pharaſaicall, and ſeditious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155937:5"/> religions are as ridiculous and as changeable as their faſhions and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires, their ungrounded zeales, their nouriſhing and feeding of the vulgar and rebellious of the Clergie, thoſe illiterate talkers in the Pulpit will, <hi>niſi ſupra omnia ſit veritas,</hi> if the God of truth doe not ſpeedily offend, be ſtronger then either <hi>King</hi> or Church <hi>David</hi> although a man of valour and pietie, yet complaines he that the ſonnes of <hi>Zervia</hi> were to hard for him. But our Kings and Church may both complaine of the daughters of this Land. That they are and will be to hard for us, <hi>niſi ſupra omnia veritas,</hi> unleſſe God ſupport the integrity of our King, and the ſincerity of the Proteſtant Religion. A more pregnant place for the power of Kings is in <hi>Wiſdome</hi> 26 2. ſpeaking of the extreme vengeance which God will bring upon the heads of evill Kings at the laſt day, he proves the certainty thereof by an argument which will ſeeme very ſtrange in theſe rebellious dayes: <hi>Quoniam Dominus non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vebitur faciem cujuſque,</hi> unto you O Kings doe I ſpeake, hee is not afraid of the perſons of Kings, hee dares call them to account: A very vaine idle argument to prove his unmaſtered deity, and power in that he is not afraid of Kings. Who is afraid of them? Doth God indeed ſay, <hi>Ego dixi Dij estis?</hi> Wee can take up the next verſe and be even with him, he ſhall fall when we pleaſe) like one of the Princes. No ſuch great matter of feare is the perſon or power of a King now a dayes, when every poore ignorant peſant, or ſhop-man can define, confine, and pinch up the prerogative of the King, when the vulgar Clergie, thoſe <hi>Gibeanites,</hi> not fit to draw water for learned men, can pricke and gird the perſon of the King for the ſpace of three or foure houres. When every petty but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Towne can neglect, if not contemne his preſence when be vouchſafes to come and ſee us. So that if God will prove his ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to us, hee muſt quit the old argument of feare due unto Kings, from all but himſelfe, and fetch one ſutable to our late religions and governments in Church and Common-Wealth; As that he is not afraid of the Popes holineſſe, or of a presbysteriall diſcipline, or a popular diſcipline. Thus Scripture and reaſon the arguments of the wiſe muſt bee turned to and fro, to follow the unconſtant humour of this preſent world. But we in feare of God, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his King, will lay the ground of our allegiance faſt, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155937:5"/> ſuch as whereupon wee may build up a peece of obedience that may procure us a Crowne of immortality at the laſt day, by Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> rule, <hi>arceſſemus Rivum fidelitatis de fonte pietatis,</hi> not only from cuſtomes and fundamentall lawes in a private land, who are moſt-what both imperfect and obſcure, but from the plaine and eaſie Text of Gods owne Law, which as it is ſufficient for any mans ſalvation, without the blaſphemous expoſitions of theſe times. So in the point of obedience unto <hi>Kings</hi> (a maine principle in Chriſtian doctrine) <hi>without which no man ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven</hi>) it is very plentifull and plaine among the reſt, this is one, <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The word of a King.</head>
               <p>IT <hi>is as the roaring of a Lion.</hi> It is <hi>Divalis juſſio,</hi> ſay the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, <hi>Eloquium divinum eſt in ore regis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay</hi> cites, three fundamentall lawes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in honour of the word of a <hi>KING. Si quis in alterius quam regis verba jurave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit capitale eſto. Si quis in juſſu regis</hi> (without his word) <hi>homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in armis habuerit, morte crimen, expiatur. Solius Regis nomine jus onme redditur, conventus judicatur, concilia convocanter.</hi> But I choſe rather to apply my ſelfe to Gods Word, and then will prove the power of the word of a <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two powers of <hi>Kings</hi> plaine in two places of Gods Word, the firſt is <hi>Potestas.</hi> What hee may and ought to doe in equitie, <hi>That is ſet downe,</hi> In capite volum, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. The ſecond is <hi>Potentia jus impunitatis,</hi> what he may doe, and yet may not be queſtioned by his ſubjects for ſo doing. This is in, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.12. and to the 19. The former is his owne rule, as he will anſwer God if he tranſgreſſe, the latter is his peoples rule for their obedience. The former power what is religious and juſt towards God and his people, his grave Divines, and skilfull Lawyers who are about his perſon are bound to explaine. The one to rehearſe. <hi>Otho Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis</hi> his ſentence to him or ſuch like concerning the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Cum horre dum ſit omni mortali incidere in manus dei viven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Regibus tamen eo erit horribilius, quo ipſi caeteris poſſent peccare liberius.</hi> They ſhould be informed that <hi>Kings</hi> come from Chriſts owne thigh, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19. <hi>On his thigh is written King of Kings,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155937:6"/> and Lord of Lords,</hi> That they come from the thigh of God, their government ought to bee paternall and eaſie, to uſe his ſubjects as his owne Children, as God uſeth man; that they ought not to weare <hi>Reheboams</hi> fingers, much leſſe his Fathers loynes, but <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams,</hi> yea Chriſts loynes more compaſſionate and kinde to his people under the time of Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitie then before: That their Scepters are not given them to diſh out the braines of their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſubjects, but that it was derived from <hi>Davids</hi> ſheep-hooke to lead his people by the waters of comfort, that the people are not to be goared with whips and Scorpions, and intolerable taxes and oppreſſions but to be led like ſheepe by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> That they are anointed with oyle, in token to make glad the hearts of all their ſubjects, not beſmeare them ore with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And not only religion, but alſo in Policie his Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and Lawyers are bound in Conſcience to exhort him to keep within the bounds of equity and imperrall right. <hi>Catose</hi> counſell oft repeated to him. <hi>Potentes parce uti debere poteſtate ut diu poſſint</hi> They ought to adviſe him that few Lawes whether in Church or Common wealth are admirable preſervatives both of Kings and kingdoms The government of the <hi>Iewes</hi> had not continued long under the Ceremoniall Law (the burden too heavie for them to beare) had not God watched over them with ſevere judgements. And if many Lawes be enacted, and thoſe not cloſely united to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but only depending on the <hi>placitum</hi> of the Law-maker, if alſo thereby he tye both their Conſciences and purſes (to which the Conſciences of moſt men are tyed) it is not morally poſſible, but ſuch a kingdome by the malice of men will ſhortly after bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. They ought to informe that he ought to rule <hi>more Turcico</hi> His people are not <hi>mancipia,</hi> nor <hi>more valdeſiano,</hi> they have poſſeſſions under him; neither <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without fault in the ſubject to be in his power: But that his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in ſubordination and ſubjection only. That a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump a little oppreſſion makes all his ſubjects ſource, eſpecially if the people bee aforehand ſeaſoned with the leaven of the Phariſees, with hypocriſie, who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Religion ſsave names of faith and tread-water-grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations, markes of Election of their owne chooſing, reprobating
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155937:6"/> all beſides themſelves even Kings if they pleaſe them not, <hi>having the forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof,</hi> even the power the Kings. The power they are bound to adviſe the <hi>King</hi> of who are imployed about his perſon; Wee who have to deale with the people are bound to deliver his <hi>ſecundam</hi> power <hi>nifi impunitatis,</hi> who may ſay unto the King if he doe amiſſe, <hi>What doeſt thou,</hi> Kings are not to be queſtioned.</p>
               <p>The firſt wee finde in this ſacrilegious, forme to <hi>Moſes</hi> a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie, no King was, <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices, and as their way was not the common way of obedient ſubjects, ſo neither was their death the common death of men. For ſay they could charge <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> with intruſion into their rights, muſt the form needs be by the way of queſtion interrogative. <hi>Cur elevamini,</hi> there are many other wayes to have done it more meekely: and if you marke it, it is no ordinary <hi>quare lamma,</hi> but an imperious terme, <hi>umaddans,</hi> what is the reaſon; <hi>Ephori</hi> like, we require an account of the adminiſtration of the Common wealth. This ſaucy forme of queſtioning the Jewes kept till our Sauiours time: <hi>Is not this the Carpenters ſonne. Is it lawfull to pay tribute unto Caeſar, who made thee a ruler over us.</hi> It was the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> forme in Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine: Quid nobis imperatores?</hi> It is the Popes forme. It is the Presbyterians-factious form. It is the devils form of coming to Kings with inſolent queſtions? <hi>Quid agis,</hi> we expect ſatisfaction not the word of a King only, for what hath bin governed amiſſe. <hi>Quanquam dignus ſit haec contum lia, &amp;c.</hi> Here in the Text is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as large, though not as unreaſonable, and that in the ſame way by way of queſtion. <hi>Who may ſay unto him?</hi> 1. <hi>Quis e clero?</hi> 2. <hi>Quis ex optimatibus.</hi> 3. <hi>Quis e Magiſtratibus regni.</hi> 4. <hi>Ques e Populo?</hi> may dare ſay to Him, Him annointed with oyle for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie and continuance in his Throne! Him! <hi>unctum</hi> but <hi>Chriſtum Domini,</hi> Him? Not man but God? what ſubject? what profane perſon? what mortall man may dare ſay unto him? <hi>What doeſt thou.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>I. Quis e Clero</head>
               <p>WHo of all the Church for matters of Religion or Sacriledge may queſtion the authoritie of a <hi>King.</hi> Begin wee with our Lord and Maſter of Religion, our Saviour Chriſt, hee ſuffered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155937:7"/> not Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to reſiſt the Magiſtrate: Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> reprehends both <hi>Moſes</hi> and Saint <hi>Peter, Contra Manich: ille fraterno, hic do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manico amore peccavit: nec pro fratre, nec pro Chriſto, ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nec pro Christi Religione eſt adverſus principes machinandi locus. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> to the yeare of Chriſt 350. ſaith that in the purer times of Chriſtians <hi>non cogitaverunt de vindicta,</hi> for ſaith <hi>Tertul.</hi> If <hi>malum malo diſpungi,</hi> were lawfull in Chriſtians, <hi>Nos implevimus caſtra urbes, oppida, &amp;c.</hi> wee had all the Garriſons and fortes of the kingdome, <hi>una nox pauculis faculis,</hi> wee could have lighted our cruell Tyrants to their graves. Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> gave up the Towne to Iulian the Apoſtate even when they might have defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt him, he rather by teares, and prayers, beſeecheth him to ſpare the Chriſtians. Famous is Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his obedience to <hi>Theodoſius, Suadeo rogo, hortor, admoneo,</hi> no more to a <hi>King Ego in te contumaciae animam non habeo, ſed habeo timoris,</hi> and when <hi>Valentine</hi> demanded his Church, he anſwers the <hi>King,</hi> that by right, thou canſt not take away the houſe of a private man (neither can be) and thinke you by your power to take away the Houſe of God, yet marke, <hi>imperatori non done, ſed non nego, tradere baſilicant poſſum, ſed pugnare non debeo, volens nunquam jus deſeram co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actus repugnare non novi, dolere potero, potero gemire, aliter nec debeo nec poſſum reſiſtere</hi> But excelling all theſe is the practice of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Samuel</hi> towards, <hi>Saul</hi> who was neither Prieſt nor Chriſtian, I <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. when <hi>Sauls</hi> kingdome was rent from him, <hi>decreto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> hee requeſted <hi>Samuel</hi> to ſtay and intreat God for him. No, <hi>Perjecisti Sermonem domini &amp; projecit te dominus ne ſis Rex ſuper Iſrael, Saul</hi> catcheth at him and rent his mantle. <hi>Samuel</hi> replies, <hi>The Lord hath rent the kingdome of Iſrael from thee this day.</hi> Then ſaith <hi>Saul, I have ſinned, honour me I pray thee before the Elders of my people:</hi> Here <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtayed, and returned and followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vices of Idolatrie of a <hi>King</hi> may not be remonſtrated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared down to the people, by any member of the Church of <hi>God,</hi> we muſt honour him before the people and Elders in Iſrael. Yea though he rend off our mantles from our backes, although hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of all our revenewes, we muſt with St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſay, if all the world ſhould importune me, to diſhonour the perſon of <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:155937:7"/> for his ſacriledge, <hi>Ego tamen Deum timerem.</hi> Oh that our popular Clergie either would or could looke beyond <hi>Luther.</hi> They might then learn more manners towards Kings, from <hi>Irenaeus, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Chryſoſtome, Baſil</hi> and to qualifie their ignorant zeales or their malicious knowledge. Let them take one rule for all to ſpeake honourably of the perſons of KINGS from <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> in his diſcourſe with <hi>Conſtans</hi> the <hi>Arrian.</hi> He doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime him <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or an Idolater, or (<hi>quod quidam fecit</hi>) <hi>That Tophet is prepared of old, and for the King.</hi> I dare not begin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckon, <hi>opus erit viatico.</hi> But <hi>benignifica natura tua, Domine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſte, intelligit ſingularis &amp; admirabilis ſapientia tua, aequum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri debet ſanctitati tuae glorioſiſſime Auguſte, dignantiſſime impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſancte Rex, loquuturus ſum tecum, cum honore regni &amp; fideitus,</hi> and theſe honourable termes to an <hi>Arrian.</hi> And 4. hundred Fathers of the Church ſpake no other language at <hi>Ariminum</hi> to an <hi>Arrian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Church of God is as the Jewiſh Temple twice built. And as at the latter raiſing of it, the old men who had ſeene the glory of the former wept in memory of it, for I doubt not but the grave Divines in this, and other Churches, who have ſeene the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the former part of the Church in the writings of the fathers, doe weepe to ſee it in this latter age built up indeed of ſpecious names, and outſides of Religion, but all operative faith, devotion Chaſtity, Temperance, Patience, Obedience even to Kings is made a queſtion. The Pope he lead is in the front of the latter part of the Church againſt the right of the Kings. Hee that in former times ſware, <hi>in eo per quem reges regnant,</hi> He whom the <hi>Florentine</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory can informe, that his ſupremacie was not derived from an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure place of Scripture or two. But from the Emperours remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Court from <hi>Ravenna;</hi> ſince which time not Kings, but Popes are Gods; and the Societie of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that ſlaughter-Houſe of Kings, can change a Text for his holineſſe, <hi>My ſone feare thou God and the Pope,</hi> Church-men are exempt from the power of Kings ſaith <hi>Samuel Sa.</hi> A Ieſuite: A Roman Catholike rebelling is no traytor ſaith the ſame <hi>Samuel Sa. Sexcentis verſibus eorum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puritas traloqu nemo poteſt,</hi> in ſo much as tis a proverb in <hi>Quiccar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> it is the propertie of the Church to hate the King.</p>
               <p>There is in theſe latter times another faction againſt the King
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155937:8"/> who cry, but with the <hi>Donatiſts, Quid nobis imperatori?</hi> And as the Papiſts. <hi>Dominus Deus noſter papa,</hi> ſo theſe <hi>Dominus Deus noſter conſiſtorium, presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erianum.</hi> But that you ever ſufficiently deteſt that kind of government, I will give you one of their phraſes from the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> their Church (ſay they) is the houſe (or rather their private houſes the Church) and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth but the hangings, now the hangings muſt be made fit for the houſe not the houſe for the hangings. And if the <hi>King</hi> and his Princes be too high for their holy houſe, they muſt cut them ſhorter and with the help of an Anabaptiſt lay them even with the ground But we have as yet no ſuch rebellious cuſtome, nor I hope ever ſhall; nor the Churches to God. Let the Clergie for their obedience imitate holy <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul, Eliah</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> who by ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion told him, not his people of his ſinnes. Imitate <hi>Jeremie</hi> in the priſon, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the denne. <hi>Amos</hi> ſtrucke through the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Zacharias</hi> murthered betweene the porch and the Altar, Chriſt our Maſter under <hi>Herod, Tiberius,</hi> ſuffering under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> the Apoſtles under <hi>Caligula, Claudius, Nero, Domitian,</hi> Saint <hi>John</hi> in a Tubbe of Oyle, Chriſtian Biſhops for many hundred yeares under Tyrants, Idolaters, Atheiſts, none of all theſe reviled their Princes, while they were alive. Laſt of all remember that Saint <hi>Bernard, Fidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onorum amiſſione, exilio, morte non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, terramincolo, quaſi ſemper migraturus.</hi> And Saint <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> In <hi>Epiſtola ad Cyrac:</hi> will the King or the Queene baniſh me. <hi>The earth is the Loras and the fulneſſe thereof;</hi> will hee cutt me in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? I can remember <hi>Eſay,</hi> will hee caſt me into the Sea? <hi>Ionas.</hi> If into the furnance? The three Children. If to the Lions? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</hi> If ſtone me? Saint <hi>Stephen.</hi> If behead mee? Saint <hi>John,</hi> Laſtly (for I dare not rebell) will hee take away my whole eſtate and ſubſtance from mee? that of <hi>Iob, nudus exivi ex utero matris meae &amp; nudus revertar.</hi> This for the Church: <hi>Quis e clero,</hi> if like the Primitive Fathers, may ſay unto the King, <hi>Quid agis? What doeſt thou?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155937:8"/>
               <head>2. Quis ex optimatibus regni? May ſay unto the <hi>KING</hi> what doeſt thou.</head>
               <p>Were it not thinke you a very ungratefull ſight to behold a Bull or an Vnicorne puſhing at the Lion? or the Falcon to ſeize upon the Eagle? So, and much more unſeemely were it for the Princes of the Land to queſtion their naturall King, or to reprehend his government, otherwiſe then by adviſe and humble intreatie. And here I have no minde at this time to undervalue the perſons and honours of the Princes of the Land, though but in a comparative way, in that the people will conceive all ſpoken abſolutely, which may be delivered by way of compariſon, and with the King only, <hi>pro quo caeteri, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo have their lives in no honour. And their deaths in contempt and deriſion, a fault too generall in this kingdome at this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> a Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Iſrael ſlew his Maſter, he had peace becauſe he had a Commiſſion ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Martyr.</hi> But had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace that ſlew his Maſter? <hi>David</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> under <hi>Saul</hi> tooke up foure hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men, but with no intent to oppoſe the perſon of <hi>Saul,</hi> but to preſerve himſelfe: And <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> grants that to have beene lawfull under the government and law of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which is not under the law of Chriſtians we being bound to more perfect pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and obedience in regard of better promiſes concerning ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kingdome, ſo that <hi>David</hi> caſe is no preſident for us; moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there is no neceſſitie to thinke that <hi>David</hi> intended ſo much as a defenſive war againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> but rather as the Iewes under <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> to depart into the wilderneſſe; and defend himſelfe againſt the wild beaſts, or to take ſome townes of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> untill the day of the death of <hi>Saul;</hi> Thus <hi>dum timuit oleum ſervavit inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum:</hi> All that <hi>David</hi> did when he could have cut his throate, was that he cut off the skirt of his garment, and even of this he repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>percuſſit eum cor ejus:</hi> And it is this day a tradition amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyranus,</hi> that <hi>David</hi> was puniſhed in his death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively to this ſinne, that no clothes could keepe him warme, <hi>quia oram vestis Sauli abſcidit, in vestibus, quibus opertus erat, non calefiebat.</hi> There is ground for this in the booke of <hi>Kings:</hi> But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155937:9"/> whether true or no, <hi>ficta arguunt,</hi> the morall is good. <hi>Princeps non eſt auſteroris verbienſe faedandus, nec vel ultimae ſuper fluae actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis corum quaſi finbriam vituperando decorpere preſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> a Prince <hi>Davids</hi> ſonne rebells with the raireſt pretence, that both Religion and Juſtice could make for him, forſooth that neither were duely executed in the land; he would doe it, yea and that ſpeedily, in the gates of the Citie; but marke his end, <hi>ſuſpenſus erat quaſi in patibulo,</hi> he was gibbeted without a Hangman, <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixus tribus ſagittis.</hi> 1. For diſobedience to his naturall Father, 2. For oppoſing his naturall Soveraigne. 3. For ſpoyling both Church and ſtate, under ſhew of Religion and Juſtice even when he lay with his Fathers Concubines upon the houſe toppe: And let all the enemies of the Lord the <hi>King</hi> bee as the young man is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>3. Quis e Magiſtratibus regni? May ſay unto the <hi>King</hi> what doeſt thou?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A vinculis delictorum liberi ſunt reges</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> to moderate the zeale of any inferour Magiſtrate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, if they command any thing, it is not to command but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and obedience to them, <hi>proficiet ad paenam non ad premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quam ad contumeliam pertinet creatoris ut contempto Domino co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamur ſerai &amp; ſpreto imperatore adorentur comites.</hi> No counſell or <hi>Sanedrim</hi> could lawfully queſtion <hi>Moſes;</hi> who was no King but <hi>Legatus Dei.</hi> Howſoever <hi>Philo</hi> in honour of him ſtiles him <hi>King.</hi> There is no queſtion but the generall counſell of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is the moſt incomparable <hi>medium</hi> of preferring both <hi>King</hi> and people, that the reaſon of man can poſſibly invent: But then the power of it muſt be onely <hi>directive</hi> not <hi>coercive.</hi> For I would aske by what law? by the <hi>Kings?</hi> No man is bound to give a prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall judgement againſt himſelfe, and if any equall have no power over an equall much leſſe an inferior over a ſuperior. Lawes made by the <hi>King</hi> are not <hi>Buchanans,</hi> to tye him down under the judgement and cenſure of his people, but they are Organs or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the power that governeth, at once thereby to reach the whole people, not coactively to binde the <hi>legislator,</hi> for the <hi>K.</hi> In whom humane power doth reſide, is a perſon that cannot by his owne power be controlled much leſte by the power of any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; moreover every active abilitie whether in nature or in morals
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155937:9"/> is <hi>(per ſe)</hi> cauſe or principall of alteration corruptively in another body, not in the body in the which it ſelfe reſides. Wherefore if Divines or Lawyers affirme obligation in Princes to their laws, they teach herein only the bond of conſcience. They are not <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nei judices,</hi> they appeale ſtraight to God. <hi>Tibi ſoli peccavi.</hi> But to put an end to all queſtioning of <hi>Kings</hi> by any under Magiſtrate whatſoever; I require an anſwer to the Law of God in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing queſtions. Who queſtioned <hi>Saul</hi> for ſlaying the Prieſts? did the <hi>Sanedrim?</hi> who queſtioned <hi>Salomon</hi> for his revolt to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry? did the <hi>Sanedrim?</hi> who queſtioned <hi>Ioram</hi> a Paracide, and 6. times a murtherer of his Nobles? did the <hi>Sanedrim?</hi> who Ioas for his Idolatry and ſlaying the High Prieſt did the <hi>Sanedrim?</hi> who queſtioned <hi>Theodoſius</hi> for murthering 6000. innocent ſoules? who queſtioned <hi>Conſtance, Valens? Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate?</hi> who traduced their perſons and dignities? who offered them tumultuous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts? unleſſe wee will skill more in Religion then the former part of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian world, <hi>Deſinamus ogganire, &amp; plura reges percontari.</hi> Remember that of <hi>Cicero Regum haec ſunt imperia animadverte, &amp; edicto pare, &amp; preter rogitatum ſi loquare moriere.</hi> And that of the Perſian <hi>King, mementote parendum vobis eſſe magis quam ſuadendum,</hi> even the fundamentall lawes of this kingdome, are by chance or good providence, plaine for the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned power of the <hi>King,</hi> by any lower Magiſtrate; <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Walſingham</hi> ſpeakes from a Parliament held at <hi>Lincolne, An.</hi> 130. That the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> from their preeminence and cuſtome at all times have not to anſwer before any Judge either Eccleſiaſticall or civill. And <hi>Henry</hi> or <hi>Brachton</hi> cites a fundamentall of this land, that if any thing bee to bee obtained of the <hi>King (Cum breve non currat contra Regem)</hi> there is nothing left to them but intreatie and prayers, that hee would correct himſelfe; which if hee pleaſe not to doe it is enough that he expect the Lord from heaven as his only revengers. <hi>De Chartis Regis facta Regum nec juſticiaris nec pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae perſonae debent diſputare.</hi> For certainely if there be in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, a reluctancie between two governments each watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its advantage and prioritie, it cannot be but as <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtrugled in the wombe; ſo theſe in the ſtate will breed convulſion fits, each contending who ſhall come forth in government, one of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155937:10"/> them at length will come forth with ſcarlet ſtrings on his hands and bloudie banners. If a body have two heads they will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily agree upon motion. To end this queſtioning by Magiſtrates wee will call <hi>Tertullian. Reges ſunt ſuper omnes homines &amp; ante omnes Deos:</hi> And that proverb of the <hi>Rabines, Nulla Creatura Iudicat Rogem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Quis e populo, May dare ſay unto the KING what doest thou.</head>
               <p>GOd bleſſe this poore people, it is <hi>totus in queſtionibus,</hi> buſie in ſpeculations &amp; queſtions concerning things that do not much concerne them, they have beene in Divinitie long agoe, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faith onely, or good workes juſtifie, and ſuch like queſtions, the Divines have been vehement in thoſe diſputes, and the people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivd ſtraight matter of ſalvation to be in the knowledge of them, then they undertake to diſcuſſe the queſtion, in concluſion believe nothing but their own phantaſies, and reſolve to do no good works at all: Then whether the Common-prayer be not diſervice, new Engliſh, for the new Religion, of whom it may be fitly ſaid as <hi>Tullie</hi> of <hi>Antho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> for his <hi>pientiſſimus, quod verbum latino ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone non est, id ad tuam ſingularem pretatem exprimendam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum eſt:</hi> Whether kneeling at the Sacrament (that <hi>tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum myſterium</hi> of the commemoration of Chriſts paſſion bee not Idolatry; whether Jeſu-worſhip be lawfull, and that reſolved to their hands, whether to worſhip God in entrance to his houſe in the preſence of his Angels, ſaith <hi>Terullian,</hi> be not <hi>ſuperſtitione, O tempora.</hi> Whether we may repeate the Lords Prayer that Idol? <hi>O mores,</hi> whether the ſigne of the Croſſe, uſed in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time be not now popery. <hi>O ridiculum!</hi> but I may not excuſſe the reſt by name ſo few, come wee neerer to the Text, whether if our Clergie will not preach unto us ſuch Phariſiacall, ſeditious, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, Diabolicall doctrine, wee may not chuſe others in a caſe ſo concerning the deſtruction of our ſoules. And then whether if the King Himſelfe will not conforme to our vaine ſenſeleſſe religions, (ſo many now for number infinite, for qualitie ſo blaſphemous that it is impoſſible for one man to know them all, and for rationall man
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155937:10"/> to practice any of them) wee may not queſtion his government? whether to make the queſtion more ſemblable) a <hi>King</hi> in a State, bee not like a Marriner in a ſhip? if one will not, another muſt. The Marriners thought ſo in the laſt tumult, <hi>vix vera eſſe niſi cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctanter crederem, niſi his oculis videram.</hi> In ſum, whether both for Religion and civil policie we may not as we have done to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, ſo to the <hi>King</hi> put up inſolent queſtions. <hi>Quid agis? Why doſt thou rule otherwiſe then we pleaſe to be ruled our ſelves. O that my head were a fountaine of teares,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jerem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> For Religion.</head>
               <p>We read of rebellion intended againſt <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> 2 <hi>Heſter</hi> ver. 21.22. No reaſon ſet downe, but <hi>in diebus illis,</hi> and what were thoſe dayes? you might know them by the ſtory. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> had married <hi>Eſter</hi> his Queene a vertuous woman, but of another Religion. <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Thares,</hi> Tis like were croſſed in the match, but ſee they draw their arguments from popular heads, to intereſt 127. provinces in the rebellion. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> our King matcheth with a Jew, one of a Religion hated among us, one that cares neither for <hi>Mithra</hi> nor <hi>Wamaſdres,</hi> one brought in to ruinate the eſtablish'd religion in <hi>Perſia,</hi> which by our Law ought not to be altered. Thus they are zealous on the ſuddaine, as the faſhion of the world is; This jealouſie delivered downe and digeſted by a prevailing facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the people, they forthwith (although there be no cauſe) are ready <hi>tumultuatim</hi> to runne up to the King with <hi>Quid agis?</hi> Why doſt thou change our Religion. Good people) for ſo I may rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically call them) if you intend a new religion take not rebellion in your way, for a thing that I will tell you in <hi>Luthers</hi> reformation, when was more need then now is, the rule of obedience was not duely obſerved, and there fell in or upon that reformation 100. thouſand of the people, before then that you need a reformation, before you adventure upon the dangers. <hi>Barclay</hi> accuſeth <hi>Luther</hi> for it, I dare not defend him, I finde him in his booke, <hi>Contra regem Angliae,</hi> very familiar and impudent to the King, <hi>ſtoliditas veſtra, aſinitas veſtra, cornicula avum, aut regem naſci aut fatuum;</hi> and I wiſh there be no ſuch <hi>Sheimies</hi> ſuch felly tounged reformers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155937:11"/> abroad in this our pious reformation. <hi>Barclay</hi> chargeth <hi>Luther,</hi> yet farther of the death of all thoſe people, that when he had mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them to rebellion, and could not accompliſh his owne ends, he was the firſt that moved the Magiſtrate to ruine and deſtroy them, all how true God knowes, but this the people may know is true in Policie in States men, under the larve of Religion to draw the people to one ſide, but if they faile in their plots and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Projects, they to preferre themſelves muſt be the firſt and moſt active in cutting the peoples Throates whom they have ſtirred up.</p>
               <p>Againe, in the Reformation after the death of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and there iſſued forth ſo many Schiſmes from the <hi>Anarchie,</hi> that holy <hi>Melancton</hi> who loved not Poperie confeſſed for uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, they muſt all returne to the Church of Rome againe and <hi>Prot:</hi> in his <hi>An:</hi> on <hi>Caſſ: Porf:</hi> ſpeaks little leſſe, better to endure one extreamitie then Twentie, better admit of one tyrannicall Religion then a hundred. And I pray God it bee not the effect, and reſultance of our many Schiſmes and diſtractions in our Church at this day. To come with queſtions contradiction to a King, for Religion was not heard of in the Iewiſh Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Law in <hi>Deutren mie</hi> 13.6. <hi>was if thy brother or thy ſonne, or thy wife, or thy friend intice thee to Idolatry, ſiſtas cosco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram judice,</hi> not if thy Father, or thy Husband, or thy Judge, for certaine not thy King. The manner of <hi>Balthaſars</hi> depoſition for abuſing Gods Religion and Temple, is very remarkable by all good Subjects. None of his Subjects muſt dare to draw up the order no, a hand writing out of the wall from God, muſt declare it, and when it was there none of all the people were able to read it, ſo ſtrange a thing to a ſubject is a depoſition of his King, no nor the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> nor <hi>South-ſayers,</hi> no nor the Devill himſelfe is able to underſtand it. <hi>Daniell</hi> is ſent for, he only by divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is able to read, and what is it. <hi>Mene, Mene, tekell uparſin,</hi> God not the people hath numbred thy Kingdome and finiſhed it, <hi>Joſeph</hi> 17. <hi>chap.</hi> 36. Tells us of the ſect of the Phariſees, who to the number of ſixe thouſand in zeale to their hypocriticall Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were in a covenant by themſelves againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſome of that number came to our Saviour with that queſtion (for that is ſtill
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155937:11"/> their forme) <hi>is it lawfull to give Tribute unto Caeſar.</hi> They are reſolved not to doe it before, and theſe Sectaries proved the ruine of the Iewiſh Government, with whom Docter <hi>Iackſon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the Schiſmaticks, of his, and theſe times, growing on ſo faſt, that both he and Sir <hi>Walter Ral.</hi> 2. Hiſt. ſpake out of propheticke wiſdome, that they would hazard the ruine both of this Church and State, and they would force it into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and confuſion. For indeed what elſe can bee expected, when every one may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his owne Religion, and ſuch a one as may encourage him to contradict the eſtabliſhed government of the Church, on the one hand, and the fundamentall <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land bee obſcured on the other, and the Majeſtie and power of the Kings perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, what remaines but we may ſay over this Church as <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurtha</hi> over Rome. <hi>O urbem venalem &amp; lite perituram ſi empto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem invenerit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> For Civill Government.</head>
               <p>As the people for Religion may not queſtion the King, ſo neither for the policie and civill affaires, may they ſay unto him, <hi>what do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou.</hi> And here the people are furniſhed (I know not whence) with as many queſtions to moleſt the quiet of the ſtate, as they have beene of late to diſturbe the peace of the Church. And firſt may not his own Lawes ſay unto him <hi>Quid agis? Directive</hi> they may <hi>coactive,</hi> they neither may nor can; if the King be in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, he can make new lawes to defend his errour, ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> and Sir <hi>Walter Ralleigh,</hi> reprehends <hi>Bracton</hi> though a Philachriſt, for ſaying that a King is King by the Law, <hi>Me ito de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet res tribuere regi quod lex attribuit ei nam lex facit ut ipſe ſit Rex.</hi> Whereas ſaith Sir <hi>Walter, Bracton</hi> aſcribes this power to humane Law, hee is miſt ken, for Kings are made by God, and Lawes Divine, and by humane Lawes are only declared to be King. But is he not a <hi>King</hi> by our election? Election doth not make him <hi>King</hi> although, unleſſe he had beene choſen he had not beene ſuch. As they are to ſay of good worke, they are <hi>via ad regnum non cauſa regnandi,</hi> ſo may wee of election, tis not the cauſe but the way to the kingdome, and ſo we find in Scripture, where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155937:12"/> choſe, God made the King it is not <hi>nos,</hi> but <hi>Ego poſui regem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Iſrael,</hi> and it was Gods admirable wiſdome, when the world could no longer ſubſist under paternall Government, in that men and malice increaſing in the world, paternall indulgences would not doe right reſpectively, every mans injuries both expreſly in the Iewiſh government and in other States by the Law of reaſon doe prompt them to elect one man as their common Father, that this one man, this common Father, this King not intereſted in private reſpects might diſtribute Iuſtice impartially, and puniſh offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in equitie: and alſo that the people by their owne act of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might bee obliged the more to obey him, although he proved rigid and auſtere, as they would and ought to obey their naturall Father, which act God evermore confirmes in Heaven, this may appeare better in a ſimilitude. Originall ſinne is remitted in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but not <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> yet if there bee no <hi>opus operatum</hi> there is (by vertue of the covenant <hi>ordinario,</hi> no remiſſion of the ſinne; and after <hi>opus operatum</hi> it is impoſſible for the Prieſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voake the ſin againe remitted in heaven. So is it in elective king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and all are ſuch naturally) the <hi>opus operatum</hi> of the people, <hi>ſc.</hi> there election doth not make the King, neither is he made King without it, and after election he is ſo made and confirmed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that their act cannot <hi>ex jure</hi> be reverſed againe. For election according to Gods Lawes, right, reaſon, is not a conditionall of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Kings downe to the peoples ends: ſo as if he anſwer not their ends, he ſhall be no longer King, but it is a reſignation of our naturall and private intereſt of revenge of all our paritie, which wee have with him, by the Law of nature into the hands of God, that he would place him <hi>ſuper nos.</hi> It might have been ſaid, as to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> was it not your owne before ſuch election and reſignation of your rights? If now you ſhall demand your right againe, and queſtion his Prerogative and immunitie, it may be ſaid as to them, <hi>why have yee lyed to the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, what if hee breake the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, to which he is ſworne. It is an old principle, <hi>Perjurium iure non ſolvit regnum, Salomon</hi> anſwers, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Rex inſipiens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det populum,</hi> not <hi>populus inſipiens prodet regem,</hi> as it is now this day. Now a King by changing the Lawes, and antient govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155937:12"/> doth civilly deſtroy the kind of his people. But what if bee be not of capacitie to underſtand the Lawes? As if the lawes bee not to be underſtood: ſuch there be in the world. But if they bee the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. tells you, <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ibi terracujus Rex puer eſt,</hi> not <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ubi Rex cuius terra, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, what if a Tyrant? may we not queſtion him then? for that <hi>injuria Tyranni eſt in facto,</hi> uſurpation of a Kingdome, not his own. <hi>Ius regis eſt in facti impunitate.</hi> God will reckon with Kings one day, for abuſing his Image in the meaneſt of his ſubjects. But if touch him; you may <hi>Athenian</hi> like expell one Tyrant, and gaine thirtie if not more. <hi>Peritt Nero ſed nullo ſucceſſu,</hi> one yeare after his death proved worſe than foureteene of his Tyrannte. And it was the Country-mans proverbe, I wiſh they had it againe, <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonum effodio,</hi> wee ſhall have a worſe maſter, a worſe King when this is gone.</p>
               <p>The Iewiſh Government was more ſubject to tyrannie then any Nation, then in the world or ſince, in that they lyed under a ſpec all forme of puniſhment, to keepe them in more perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: As if a private man offended, many of the people ſuffered death, either meritory in themſelves, for their ſinnes, though <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionaliter,</hi> from the ſinne of another perſon, or elſe from Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dominion over the temporall life of man. But if a King tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, many thouſands periſhed. 70. thouſands dyed for <hi>Davids</hi> ſinne in numbring the Souldiers, here is a ſtrange tyrannie over the lives of the ſubject, and yet <hi>David was not chaſed too and fro in his kingdome, and the power of calling his ſouldiers taken out of his hand.</hi> And yet as <hi>David</hi> ſpake, <hi>I have ſinned, let me be puniſhed, as for this people, quid fecit?</hi> So the people may invert the words, <hi>wee have ſinned and one wickedly, but for this righteous</hi> King, <hi>quid ille fecit? Daniel</hi> under the names of beaſts, foretells certaine Kings degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating into tyrannie, according to the ſeverall qualities and kindes of tyrannie. In the New Teſtament, <hi>Tell Herod the Fox.</hi> But we read not that they were depoſed of their kingdomes by their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>Pharoah</hi> ſuffered ten plagues for his tyrannie, God ſuffers not rebellion to be one, but <hi>Frogs, Locuſt, Caterpillars, Famine,</hi> ſc. <hi>Herod</hi> is deſtroyed not by ſubjects, but by <hi>Lice.</hi> It ſeemes God would not doe them the honour, as to periſh by the hands of men,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155937:13"/> not by women, <hi>Abimelechs</hi> feare, not by enemies, <hi>Sauls</hi> feare, much leſſe by ſubjects, but in <hi>ſimili,</hi> as they lived like beaſts, ſo muſt they be conſumed. Rebell not then, doe not Tyrants that to much honour expect, a while Gods potent and juſt revenge; he is beſt skild how to ſuit and proportion puniſhments to the perſons of Kings, hee can take them away by ſome contumelious death, and can ſend Arm es of <hi>Locuſts, Frogs,</hi> and ſuch baſe Vermin to deſtroy them. You ſee how eaſie it is for God to take vengeance of his owne Kings. No neede of deepe plots of many yeares contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, no neede of hearing of incumbrance, and diſtractions of your owne making, and the wrath of God to the reſt, when Flies, and Lice, and Frogges in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chamber may ſerve the turne. When as God, not the people ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> may turne <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> to graſſe among the beaſts or the fielde. And alſo that if notwithſtanding this you will deſtroy your Kings, remember whoſe places you ſupply of the moſt contemptible vermin living, you who remaining in obedience are men, not Iewes but Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans one day not men <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Kings in Gods owne kingdome, by rebellion yee make your ſelves, not Angels, not Chriſtians, not Iewes, no not men, no not beaſts of the better ſort, but Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, but Frogs, but ſtarved Kine and Lice, <hi>Nay yee ſhall bee as the dust of which God made the Lice, and the Angell of the Lord ſcattering you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was an evill cuſtome among the <hi>Goths</hi> to deſtroy their Kings upon any ſmall diſpleaſure, and <hi>Barclay</hi> tells us of a cuſtome in <hi>Burguney</hi> if they yeare brought forth no Corne they removed their King contrary to the proverb. <hi>In Tacitus, malum regem &amp; ſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lem annum aequo feramus.</hi> Kings ruled with <hi>Burgandians</hi> by a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Almanacke, I pray God we in this Land prove not <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</hi> If our luxurious and earthly pleaſures and profits be croſſd by the doctrines of the learned and pious Clergie, or by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the King though for our owne ſecuritie and peace, if we miſſe any of our former delights, then <hi>Burgundian</hi> like, <hi>Terra non peperit hoc anno, nos ilaque pariamus;</hi> what <hi>novum clerum, novum, Kegem, noves leges,</hi> new nothing, but new confuſion, new diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, new ſchiſmes, new inceſts, new (for number,) adulteries, and when after lamentable experience you ſhall compare the old and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155937:13"/> new government together, ye will ſay, as our Saviour did of wine, no man drinketh new Wine, but faith the old is better.</p>
               <p>I doe not here reprehend the whole people, I have learned more Rhetorick from <hi>Quintili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> I know many went along with <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to the paying of his vow who were not in the rebellion, many both menand women are like the Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus</hi> whoſe hearts are warme within zealous for the truth, but their eyes are holden by the ſeditious ignorant Miniſters of the times, that they cannot ſee the true face of Chriſtianitie: No I ſpeake not to theſe, but I ſpeake to <hi>Burgundian</hi> Subjects, Almanacke ſubjects who would faine change their King with their Religion and that once a yeare at leaſt, I ſpeake to men ingaged to this earth, to their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, to their luſts, drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, gluttonie, not in the Vniverſitie onely, but in the Towne and Country; where not, who when any rate or ſubſedie for the publike good, either curb their cuſtomes in expenſive v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces, or croſſe their tenacious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours then <hi>Burgundian</hi> like, <hi>Terra non poperit hoc anno; Eteve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigio,</hi> there ariſe under thoughts of the King, they expound his actions with diſadvantage to his honour, at length come up to him boldly to him with impudent queſtions, <hi>Quid agis?</hi> why are wee governed otherwiſe, then we have a mind to be governd our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Hard, to hard is the condition of Kings, if ſo much libertie be allowed to the Subjects, if they at their unbounded pleaſure may report a religious King to be ſuperſtitious, a devout <hi>King</hi> a hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, if grave and ſerious auſtere and ſullen: if pleaſant diſſolute: if mercifull, to be defective in ſpirit and valour: if ſevere againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, tyrannicall; if bountifull (though in policie) profuſe; if provident, for his Royal poſteritie covetous; if ſuch inſolent diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may paſſe uncenſurd on the perſons of <hi>Kings,</hi> then <hi>actum eſt de regibus,</hi> down with <hi>Kings</hi> and kingdomes, Church and State, and all union among the ſons of men.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, May we not by natures principles queſtion and remove evill <hi>Kings</hi> from us as wee doe evill beaſts, for the ſecuritie of our eſtates and lives. An anſwer from nature ſhal conſure the queſtion. Drinke naturally quencheth thirſt, but if you take it in a feaver it will more inflame you, then you may not conſult with the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour appetite, but with reaſon, let bloud, purge, and potion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155937:14"/> directed by the direction of the Phyſitian, not your own ſenſe ſo in a Common-wealth diſeaſed by Tyrannie; the people may not uſe the inferiour right of private nature, for in a Common-wealth pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons have given up their private right of puniſhing, they cannot puniſh a private perſon, for certaine not the King, to whom their right is reſignd; what then, if the diſeaſe be hot upon us we wee muſt be let bloud, purge our luxuriant paſſions, our inflamed rebellious humour, remove each man his particular ſinnes, conſult with the Phyſition of States by prayers and teares, <hi>beſeech the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, who hath the hearts of Kings in his own hand, and can upon ſubmiſſion to himſelfe and his King, either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him or amend him. Haec est expediſsima via reprimendi tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidem</hi> ſaith <hi>Salibur. Peccata enim delinquentium ſunt vires tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, may not the people ſay unto the King <hi>what dost thou?</hi> Or what art thou, without the people? Are not we the ſtrength of a King? Did not <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſay to his Souldiers they were his wings, and he but the body? I deſire no greater honour to be given to the King, then to be thought the body to a paire of wings, goe ſee if he can flye without that body, ſo it may be ſaid next unto God, in the King your body yee live and move, and have your being, and for your ſtrength, it is true, yee have enough, but for what? even to eate up one another alive, as it is in the Jewiſh proverb.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, But if the people have not thoſe rights and priviledges which they enjoyd under his predeceſſors, may they not come then to him with <hi>quid agis?</hi> Firſt, all Kings in an elective kingdome by ſucceſſionare <hi>pares,</hi> they enter naturally upon <hi>jus integrum,</hi> ſo that if any rights have paſſed from former Kings pejudiciall to the Crowne, <hi>jure regni,</hi> they returne againe; yet, Secondly, if any right of the ſubjects (for rights they have) have paſſed from them to former Kings in conſideration of ſuch priviledges, it is both ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and juſt that they be recompenced or reſtored back again.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, what if he violate the conditions propounded to him and his predeceſſors upon his entrance to the Crown? may not the people queſtion him for that? Not ſo far I believe as is commonly thought <hi>ſummum imperium &amp; conditionatum,</hi> may very well bee conſeniaſanea, and not oppoſites. In the Perſian kingdome hee is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155937:14"/> ſworne to the laws of the Perſians, which ought not to alter, and yet none may queſtion him, if he violate theſe lawes. In the Jewiſh go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment wherein Kings were abſolute and uncontroleable by their ſubjects, there were ſome caſes &amp; conditions in which <hi>jure</hi> he had no power to Iudge, as <hi>de Tribu, de pontifice, de propheta,</hi> as is plain, <hi>Ier.</hi> 38.5. yet although theſe conditions were delivered by God Himſelfe, if the K. (as appeares in many places of the book of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chron.</hi>) did intermeddle it was not in the power of the <hi>Iewes</hi> to queſtion or derrive him of his government. But what if it be a condition that if he breake theſe laws he ſhall <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void his kingdom, as it hath bin in ſome States. This will be found a moſt prejudiciall condition both to King and people, for wee living in this world not by mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall demonſtrations, where there is no <hi>medium</hi> between <hi>rectum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rium,</hi> but by morall rules, where there are many <hi>formae interjectae</hi> between <hi>rectum &amp; curvum,</hi> vice and vertue. Some vertuous actions comming neere vice are deemed vitious, and ſome vicious comming mere vertue, are reckoned vertuous, it will bee very hard to know what when a <hi>King</hi> punctually keeps al his conditions, but at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a prevailing faction in the people, he will be judged either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or by conſequence to have broken the conditions on which his kingdome depends, this kinde of government muſt be very doubtfull and deſtructive to a Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, may not the people come unto the <hi>King</hi> with <hi>quid agis?</hi> if he intend and threaten to deſtroy the whole State, as <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula,</hi> or if he intend to give up himſelfe and his kingdome without the ſubjects conſent not only in <hi>Patrocinium</hi> but <hi>in ditionem,</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince. In both theſe caſes, <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> that there hath been no rebellion in the ſubject, and then the caſes are morally impoſſible; <hi>Grotius, Barclay,</hi> and <hi>Abbas, Winzelus,</hi> are of opinion that the Law of nature doth return unto the people again, both for to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and elect againe. But the <hi>holy Abbat</hi> is of a better opinion that the Law of Nature is not alwayes to be reſumd by Chriſtians, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally here where it cannot be taken, but with many inconveniences and uncertainties both from our not knowing what is a full intention and for defect of a lawfull Judge, and in regard of appeales to other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and beſide theſe a breach of many Lawes of Chriſtianitie. His advice is rather than to injure our Chriſtian profeſſion to betake our ſelves to faſting and prayers, and removing from us our particular luſts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155937:15"/> and wickedneſſe provided thus for death, expect Gods providence who never failes religious men and kingdomes in this generall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for death; either God may turne him and his armies from us, put a hooke in his noſtrills, or elſe confound his perſon with ſome ſudden judgement, even Lice may conſume his unnaturall bowells, or if not, <hi>non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cet ſed purgat,</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hee doth but haſten us to a better kingdome, an everlaſting one in heaven. <hi>Durus eſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſed tulit Iudeus, &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat Chriſtianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in the name of Religion, in the name of the peace of the Common-wealth, and the honour of the King let me aske you theſe queſtions.</p>
               <p>You that come up ſo boldly to the face of a King for the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on who ſhould <hi>clamare a facie ejus</hi> are yee ſure the Religion yee queſtion him for is the right Religion? are yee ſure your inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not from the Devill? are yee ſure your Miniſters are both for learning and manners, ſuch as in whom yee may conſide in a matter that ſo concernes your ſoules? And that they doe not humour you contrary to their owne conſciences, out of reſpect to preferment in the Church which at another time either their povertie in parts, or poverty in manners could not attaine.</p>
               <p>Are ye ſure that thoſe that from your Pulpits declaime ſo fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt ſuperſtition and Idolatry, have not themſelves beene leaders in that which they now condemne in others, and ſo cannot bee fitt Iudges what is Idolatry? Or elſe themſelves are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine are yee all of one Religion that the King may ſatisfie you all at once? If yee be not all of one Religion, tell us how many your are of if you can? And if you ſhould chance to be one Religion at any time hereafter, are yee ſure to continue in it? That the King may not bee troubled <hi>Burgundians</hi> like to eſtablish a new Religion once every yeare for you. If you be not certaine of all theſe, as I am ſure you are not, how dare yee certainely confound King, Church, and State, for an uncertaine Religion.</p>
               <p>Again for your Policy and civill government are ye certaine of the fundamentall lawes of the land? Are ye ſure ye cannot digeſt an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary government under the notion and terme of fundementall lawes? It is not an impoſſible thing in nature that, are ye ſure, if the <hi>King</hi> be not abſolute and ſole judge of fundamentall lawes to be freed from avarice and ambition in the interiour Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155937:15"/> two inſeprable vices in Aristocracy: Both which are ſatisfied in a <hi>King</hi> ambition in that he is <hi>ſummu,</hi> Avarice, in large eſtate. Are yee ſure of the ſame Senate alwayes, and if you be extreme now time may come when others may be as extreme now time may come when others may be as extreame, and ſo the kingdome hurried betweene two extreames, the peoples rule being to run from one extream unto another. Laſtly are ye ſure if ye put any more inſolent queſtions to the king, you may not turne a meek and pious King as ever ſate upon this Throne, into a Tyrant. A learned Church as ever any in this Kingdome or elſe where into ignorance. Aflouriſhing ſtat as any in the Chriſtian world into a confuſion, a long and happy peace into as long and unhappy warre? a fulneſſe into famine? your wives to widdowes? your children to Orphants? your ſelves into your grave, and you leave this nation behind you a Deſolation a hiſſing a reproach a by word to the nations round about us.</p>
               <p>And now God forgive mee if in this diſcourſe I have not intended rather the liberties and rights of the ſubject, then the prerogative of the <hi>King,</hi> I remembred all this while what Saint <hi>August</hi> ſaith <hi>Tolle Iura Regum et quis poteſt dicere haec volla mearſt,</hi> take away the <hi>Kings</hi> ſole and abſolute government, and who can ſecure his own life and eſtat, they muſt needs, be ſubject to a thouſand alterations, I beſech you therefore by your deare and many Children, by the antient Proteſtant Religion, by the antient and fundamentall lawes in this land for obedience <hi>King,</hi> ſit down with prayers and tears, for theſe many diſtractions Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> way <hi>non ſcuta ſed fletu reparate rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub:</hi> Amend your lives be charitable and kind on to another fit downe togither in peace under your vines, as people who hope here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to fit downe in the kingdom of heaven. In a word feare God honour the <hi>King</hi> neither people nor Church nor Nobility, nor inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Magiſtrate of the land lay unto the <hi>King</hi> by the way of rebellious contradiction, <hi>What doeſt thou.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
